{"tossups": [{"question": "This country purged its military in the 2000s on the basis of the \u201cErgenekon\u201d[[ar-geh-NEH-kon]] ultra-nationalist conspiracy. In 2019, this country launched Operation Peace Spring after the U.S. pulled its support from Kurdish allies. This country has been accused of democratic backsliding and Islamism under the AKP, or Justice and Development Party, hurting their chances of joining the EU. For ten points, name this country led by Recep Tayyip Erdo\u011fan [[reh-CHEP ty-EEP EHR-duh-wahn]].", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Turkey</u></b> (or <b><u>T\u00fcrkiye</u></b> Cumhuriyeti)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In an early experimental version of this literary form, Lawrence Sterne used a page of black ink to illustrate sorrow. This form's \"sentimental\" genre is exemplified by Samuel Richardson's 1740 work,<em> Pamela; or Virtue Rewarded</em>. This form separated from the traditional romance during the early eighteenth century with the publication of<em> Moll</em> <em>Flanders</em> and<em> Robinson Crusoe</em> by Daniel Defoe. For ten points, name this lengthy form of narrative writing, typified by Jonathan Swift's<em> Gulliver's Travels</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Novel</u></b> (accept <b><u>Novel</u></b>la; accept Sentimental <b><u>Novel</u></b>; accept Travel <b><u>Novel</u></b>; prompt on \"romance\" before mentioned; prompt on answers such as \"book\")", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Vietnam veteran Kenneth Deardorff is the last man to make use of this act, facilitating his move to Alaska to open a general store along the Stony River. Horace Greeley and George Henry Evans were early advocates of this law, with the latter running on the platform of \"Vote Yourself a Farm.\" The Kinkaid Act amended this law, allowing large swaths of land to be claimed in the depopulated region of the Sandhills in western Nebraska. For ten points, name this 1862 act that allowed Americans to claim public land for free as long as they farmed it.", "answer": "<b><u>Homestead</u></b> Act of 1862 (accept <b><u>Homestead</u></b> Act[s])", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While serving as Secretary of State under this president, John Clayton negotiated a treaty with Henry Bulwer of the U.K. concerning spheres of influence in Central America. This man\u2019s daughter, Sarah, married Jefferson Davis who served under this man at the Battle of Buena Vista [[BWEH-nah VEES-tah]]. This Whig defeated Lewis Cass and Martin van Buren in the 1848 U.S. presidential election. For ten points, name this Mexican-American War hero who succeeded James K. Polk as president of the United States.", "answer": "Zachary <b><u>Taylor</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This one-time state attorney general argued in favor of the defendant in the case<em> Van</em> <em>Ordern v. Perry</em> which concerned a Ten Commandments monuments at the State House. The Anti-Defamation League censured this politician for comparing mass shootings to the Holocaust after the Sutherland Springs tragedy. This man provoked criticism when he blamed the unimplemented \"Green New Deal\" for his state's power plant failure during a 2021 ice storm. The Texas Heartbeat Act was signed by, for ten points, which Republican governor?", "answer": "Greg <b><u>Abbott</u></b> (or Gregory Wayne <b><u>Abbott</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man transformed the Italian cruiser<em> Ramb III</em> into his own personal yacht, <em>Galeb</em>. With the monarchist Chetniks, this man's forces resisted the Axis collaborationist government, including the Croatian Ustashe [[ooh-STAH-shuh]]. The Informbiro [[in-form-BEE-roh]] Period occurred after this communist leader split with Josef Stalin, and this man was later one of the founders of the \"Non-Aligned Movement.\" A united socialist Yugoslavia was led by, for ten points, which commander of the Partisans?", "answer": "Josip <b><u>Broz</u></b> <b><u>Tito</u></b> (accept either underlined portion; accept Marshal <b><u>Tito</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man created a \"Spirit Thermometer\" filled with liquor to be displayed in the court of his patron, Ferdinando II de Medici. Pope Urban VIII's [[the eighth's]] inquisitors led an investigation against this man after he published \u201cDialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems.\u201d A legends tells how this man dropped two balls of different masses off the Leaning Tower to test an Aristotelian hypothesis. Four moons of Jupiter are named for, for ten points, which Italian physicist and astronomer?", "answer": "<b><u>Galileo</u></b> <b><u>Galilei</u></b> (or <b><u>Galileo</u></b> di Vincenzo Bonaiuti de' <b><u>Galilei</u></b>; accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This nation's prime minister-in-exile gave the \"Comments on the Instructions\u201dspeech, instructing public servants to resist the orders of its Reichskommissariat [[RIKES-kohm-ee-SAHR-yaht]]. Operation Market Garden aimed to liberate this nation by capturing bridgeheads across the Rhine. During the Holocaust, diarist Anne Frank and her family lived in the \"Secret Annex\" in the capital city of, for ten points, what European nation?", "answer": "Kingdom of the <b><u>Netherlands</u></b> (or Koninkrijk der <b><u>Nederland</u></b>en; accept <b><u>Holland</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man is depicted with an adult's head and a child's body clutching an axe in a Grant Wood painting whose title figure opens a red curtain. During the War of 1812, Dolley Madison ordered her slaves to recover the Lansdowne portrait of this man. A painting of this man leading troops on a boat anachronistically contains an American flag. For ten points, name this U.S. president, who was depicted by Emanuel Leutze [[LOYT-zuh]<em> Crossing the</em> <em>Delaware</em>.", "answer": "George <b><u>Washington</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A major figure in this movement defined it in an essay titled \"Answering the Question: What is [this movement]?\" This movement's ideals were supposedly espoused by monarchs like Catherine the Great and were often spread through meetings at Masonic Lodges, coffeehouses, and salons. Preceded by Renaissance Humanism and the Scientific Revolution, for ten points, what intellectual movement of the 17th and 18th centuries was espoused by figures such as Immanuel Kant [[KAHNT]] and Voltaire?", "answer": "Age of <b><u>Enlightenment</u></b> (accept Age of <b><u>Reason</u></b>; accept word forms of <b><u>Enlightenment</u></b> such as <b><u>Enlightened</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This man described the uncertainty of ongoing battles as the \"Fog of War\" and described warfare as a \"continuation of politics by other means.\" For ten points, name this nineteenth-century German military theorist who wrote<em> On War</em>.", "answer": "Carl von <b><u>Clausewitz</u></b> [[KLAUS-vitz]] (or Carl Philip Gottfried von <b><u>Clausewitz</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Cripps mission was a failed attempt to secure this colony's full cooperation in its colonizer's World War Two efforts. This colony's Lucknow Pact united its rival Muslim League and a namesake National Congress. The last viceroy of this colony was Lord Mountbatten, who withheld support for the creation of an independent Pakistan. Gaining its independence as the culmination of the 3 June Plan was, for ten points, what subcontinental British colony?", "answer": "<b><u>India</u></b> (accept the British <b><u>Raj</u></b>; accept Direct Rule in <b><u>India</u></b>; accept Crown Rule in <b><u>India</u></b>; accept <b><u>India</u></b>n Empire; prompt on \"Bharata\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man supposedly crossed a channel while wearing chain mail in a tale told by his rival, Unferth. A band of<em> thanes</em> who abandoned this king after encountering a dragon are later exiled by his successor, Wiglaf [[VEE-glahf]]. This man tears the arms off a descendant of Cain who terrorizes the Hall of Heorot [[HEH-oh-roht]] of King Hrothgar [[HROTH-gahr]]. For ten points, name this hero of the Geats [[GEETS]] who defeats the monster Grendel in a namesake epic poem.", "answer": "<b><u>Beowulf</u></b> BONUS:<em> Beowulf</em> is written in what Middle Age language, virtually unreadable to contemporary speakers without study? ANSWER: <b><u>Old English</u></b> (accept <b><u>Anglo-Saxon</u></b>; accept <b><u>Englisc</u></b>; prompt on \"English\")", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "28 acre In this state, former U.S. Army soldier Kevin Baugh [[BAW]] founded a 1.28 acre micronation known as the Republic of Molossia. The discovery of the Comstock Lode led to a mining boom around this state's Virginia City. As a response to the Great Depression, this state legalized \"gaming\" in the 1930s. The Carson City convention led to the statehood of, for ten points, what western U.S. state?", "answer": "<b><u>Nevada</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Secretary of State Cordell Hull openly condemned a violation of this edict committed by the Free French after their seizure of Vichy-held Saint Pierre and Miquelon [[meek-LOHN]]. The refusal by Venezuela to pay back foreign debts led to a modification of this edict known as the Roosevelt Corollary. An effort to protect newly-independent Latin American nations led to, for ten points, what 1823 doctrine meant to halt European intervention in the New World?", "answer": "<b><u>Monroe</u></b> Doctrine", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The whipping of the young chief of these people led to the cannibalization of a European ship's crew, an incident known as the<em> Boyd</em> Massacre. Clans of these people are known as<em> hap\u016b</em>, and after gaining firearms from Europeans, these people fought the Musket Wars. The poorly-translated Treaty of Waitangi [[wye-TAHN-gee]] led to this people group signing away their land to British authorities. The indigenous people of New Zealand are, for ten points, what Polynesian culture?", "answer": "<b><u>M</u><u>\u0101</u><u>ori</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A passage in this book is often considered the first piece of public advocacy for</u> <u>a progressive tax. This book was written primarily to forge a new theory to replace</u> <u>the ideas of Mercantilists and Physiocrats. (+)</u> This book built upon its author's earlier</b><em><b> Theory of Moral Sentiments</b></em><b> by linking the concept of the \"Invisible Hand\" (*)</b> to production. For ten points, name this<em> magnum opus</em> of Scottish moral philosopher Adam Smith, considered a foundational text of classical economics.", "answer": "<em> The</em> <em><b><u>Wealth of Nations</u></b></em> (or<em> An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the</em> <em><b><u>Wealth of</u> </b><b><u>Nations</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>Sebastian Sommer's hypothesis that buildings along this structure combined</u> <u>human barracks with horse stables was validated by excavations in the 2000s at</u> <u>South Shields. The Vallum (+)</u> earthwork lay to the south of this structure, which added to pre-existing forts in a line from Solway Firth to the River Tyne. Picts and other Caledonian tribes lived north of this structure, which began construction in (*) </b>122 AD. For ten points, name this 73-mile barrier that formed the northern border of Roman Britain.", "answer": "<b><u>Hadrian's Wall</u></b> (accept <b><u>Vallum Aelium</u></b> or <b><u>Vallum Hadriani</u></b> before \"Vallum\"; accept <b><u>Pict's Wall</u></b> before \"Picts\"; prompt on \"Roman Wall\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>While campaigning in Juiz [[HWEZ]] de Fora, this candidate was stabbed below</u> <u>his bulletproof vest by a man who claimed to be \"on a mission from God.\" A Facebook</u> <u>group called \"Women Against\" [this politician] sparked the (+)</u></b> <em><b>Ele N\u00e3o</b></em><b> [[EH-lay \"NOW\"]] demonstration against his policies. This successor to Michel Temer [[TEM-ehr]] led the movement to remove left-leaning president Dilma Rousseff [[ROO-sef]] while serving as federal deputy of (*)</b> Rio de Janeiro. For ten points, name this man who in 2019 became the president of Brazil.", "answer": "Jair <b><u>Bolsonaro</u></b> (or Jair Messias <b><u>Bolsonaro</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Description Acceptable. A dispute over who accomplished this feat led to the</u> <u>Smithsonian wrongly attributing it to engineer Samuel Langley. This feat, which lasted</u> <u>59 seconds, (+)</u> was launched from an incline on Kill Devil Hill. Bicycle store employee Charlie Taylor built a lightweight gasoline motor to make this feat possible for the vessel</b><em><b> Flyer I</b></em><b>. Kitty Hawk, (*)</b> North Carolina was the sight of, for ten points, what feat accomplished by the Wright Brothers?", "answer": "The <b><u>First</u></b> manned, powered <b><u>Flight</u></b> by the Wright Brothers (accept the <b><u>First</u> </b>manned, powered <b><u>Flight</u></b> at Kitty Hawk; accept descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Grove and fellow Marxists</u> <u>formed this nation's</u></b><em><b><u> Partido Socialista</u></b></em><b><u>, which was overthrown in (+)</u> 1973 after the seizure of Moneda [[moh-NEH-dah]] Palace. In this country, Salvador Allende [[ah-YEHN-deh]], was replaced by a U.S.-backed military junta [[HOON-tah]]. (*)</b> For ten points, name this Andean country led for nearly twenty years by the reactionary Augusto Pinochet [[pee-noh-SHEH]].", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Chile</u></b> (or Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Chile</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This sport is depicted in a Francisco de Goya sketch showing the historical \"El</u> <u>Campeador\" El Cid performing it on horseback. The treatise</u></b><em><b><u> Death in the Afternoon</u></b></em><b><u> by</u> <u>Ernest (+)</u> Hemingway recounts the traditions surrounding this sport, particularly in Pamplona. Doctors developed a special type of surgery to deal with injuries given by (*)</b> horns to practitioners of this sport. For ten points, name this bloody sport performed in Spanish-speaking nations by<em> matadors</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Bullfight</u></b>ing (accept <b><u>Toreo</u></b>; accept <b><u>Corrida</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this presidential election year, the failure of the Republican candidate to</u> <u>visit California governor Hiram Johnson likely swung the election in the Democratic</u> <u>candidate's favor. The</u></b><em><b><u> New York World</u></b></em><b><u> wrongly reported that Charles (+)</u> Evans Hughes won this election cycle. The incumbent in this election cycle used the slogan \"He Kept Us Out of the War\" in reference to U.S. neutrality during World War One. Woodrow Wilson won (*)</b> reelection in, for ten points, which U.S. election year?", "answer": "Election of <b><u>1916</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Luwian city Carchemish [[KAR-keh-mish]] was one of the central cities of</u> <u>this empire. It's not in India, but this empire introduced iron (+)</u> smelting on a large scale to its neighbors. This empire's King Muwatalli II [[moo-wuh-TAH-lee \"the second\"]] signed the earliest-known peace treaty with Rameses the Great following the Battle of Kadesh [[KAY-desh]]. Hattusa (*)</b> was the capital of, for ten points, what Bronze Age empire that dominated Anatolia?", "answer": "<b><u>Hittite</u></b> Empire (accept the <b><u>Hittite</u></b>s; accept Syro-<b><u>Hittite</u></b> States; accept <b><u>Hatti</u></b>; or <b><u>Hethite</u></b>s; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Hattusa</u></b> before mentioned [note: It is believed the \"Hittites\" referred to themselves as \"\u1e2aa-at-tu-\u0161a\"])", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's father, Yakub, was a member of a Sipahi [[sih-PAH-hee]] cavalry</u> <u>unit that dislodged the Genoese [[jeh-noh-EEZ]] from Lesbos in the 15th century.</u> <u>Andrea Doria's unwillingness to deploy his personal fleet led to the Holy League's loss</u> <u>to this admiral at the Battle of (+)</u> Preveza [[preh-VEH-zah]]. This admiral and brother of Aruj Reis [[ah-ROOJ reh-EES]] annexed the territory of Algiers while serving Suleiman the Magnificent. (*)</b> For ten points, name this Barbary corsair named, in part, for his prominent red beard.", "answer": "Hayreddin <b><u>Barbarossa</u></b> (or <b><u>H\u0131z\u0131r</u></b> Hayrettin Pasha; or <b><u>H\u0131z\u0131r</u></b> Reis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's president, William Tolbert, was killed in a 1980 coup, and Ellen</u> <u>Johnson Sirleaf was the first woman elected president of this nation. In 2018, this</u> <u>nation elected its most accomplished soccer (+)</u> player of all time, George Weah [[WEH-uh]], as president. This country and Ethiopia were the only two countries in Africa that were never colonized (*)</b> by a European power. For ten points, name this African country founded in 1822 by the American Colonization Society.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Liberia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}